Last day of חולין, Chullin, the official דף daf is 142,
but we start on
141b, קמ"א עמוד ב', Kuf Mem Alef Amud Bet, and we pick
up with, where were we? עד כמה משלחה, Ad kama meshalecha, 1,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7 lines down in the wide lines,
line starts with the word עד ad and we pick up עד
כמה משלחה. ad kama meshalecha. Until how—until when do you have to
send it away? Which means not how many times, that was in
the משנה, Mishnah, but what is considered to be that you sent
it away? How far away does the bird have to go? So
let's take a look. אמר רב יהודה כדי שתצא מתחת ידו, Amar
Rav Yehuda: Kedei shetitzei mitachat yado,
as long as it leaves your hands. You hold it and release
it, it flies a little bit out of your hands and you're
done. The relevance of this is not only when have you done
the מצוה, mitzvah, but also as we're going to see a little
bit ironically, that as soon as you've done the מצוה, mitzvah, now
you've sent away the mother bird, now you can capture the mother
bird. She's no longer על הבנים al habanim and now you can
capture her. So talking about issues that we've been raising about the
values versus the technical הלכה, halacha, that's an issue that is going
to come up. Now, but if she goes back?
If she goes back,
well that was a discussion which I actually should have looked up
but I didn't, which is the question of once you've taken possession
of the eggs or the chicks, presumably this was the point that
רבי מאיר Rebbi Meir made, presumably even if she goes back, it's
no longer the context of the פסוק. pasuk. It's not על הבנים,
al habanim, you now own the chicks and so on. So presumably
the going back is only before you've taken possession. And once you've
sent her away, even if you haven't yet taken possession of the
chicks, you fulfilled your מצוה. mitzvah. Oh, you're right, you fulfilled your
מצוה, mitzvah, so if she comes back, you would have—if you haven't
taken possession, you'd have to send her away. That's the משנה. Mishnah.
But if you sent her away and she hasn't come back, now
you can grab her. So you take the mother bird, you release
her, she goes a foot or an inch and then you grab
her. So it's pretty funny how you can subvert the value here
by technically doing the מצוה. mitzvah. Alright, let's take a look.
So where were we? עד כמה משלחה, Ad kama meshalecha, אמר רב
יהודה כדי שתצא מתחת ידו. Amar Rav Yehuda: Kedei shetitzei mitachat yado.
במה משלחה? Bemei meshalecha? How do you send her out? So we'll
see two explanations of this. רב הונא אמר ברגליה, Rav Huna amar:
Beragleha, her legs. רב יהודה אמר באגפיה, Rav Yehuda amar: Beagapicha, her
wings. Now what does this mean?
It could mean—one explanation רש"י Rashi has is you hold the wings
and release them, or you hold the legs and release them. Although
that's a little strange because really who would care? And it's also
not going to fit into the verse afterwards. The better interpretation that
רש"י Rashi prefers is, do you have to—let's say she can't fly.
She broke her wings, you broke the wings, but she can walk
away. Is it considered sending her away if she can only walk
away or does she have to fly away in order to be
considered that you've sent her away? So ברגליה beragleha means even if
she walks?
Even if she can only walk away.
רב הונא אמר
ברגליה,
Rav
Huna amar: Beragleha, walking.
דכתיב משלחי רגל השור
והחמור, Dichitiv: Meshalechai regel hashor vehachamor,
you send the leg of the ox and the donkey. Anybody who
learned בבא קמא Bava Kamma knows that that's a פסוק pasuk that
they like in בבא קמא. Bava Kamma. Anyway, right, those of course
ox and donkey. Okay, but there you have the word שלח shaleach
to send, which has to do with walking, animals that are walking.
רב יהודה אמר באגפיה, Rav Yehuda amar: Beagapicha, her wings. דהא—now Deha
actually if you look at the side, the גרסא girsa is better—דהא
רגל דהא כנפיה נינהו. Deha regel deha knafeha ninu.
For this animal, the leg of this animal is the wings. So
yeah, by walking animals, what it means to send them, to drive
them, is to have them walk and trample, but for a bird
to send it away means to have it fly away, yes.
It could be yet another evolution
where
bird wings used to be their forelimbs.
Very interesting. Okay, everything is in the גמרא. Gemara. There you go.
Alright, so now the גמרא Gemara says: ההוא דגזינהו לגפיה ושילחה. Hahu
degazinehu lgapah veshilcha.
There was a person that broke or cut off the wings of
a bird and then released it. Now why did he do that
if he was going to release it? Because of what I've been
telling you. ואחר כך תפסה. Ve-acharach kach tafsa. And then he grabbed
it. So he basically wanted the mother bird, so he says, here's
what I'll do: I'll release it and grab it. But if I
really release it, it's going to fly away, I'm not going to
be able to grab it in time. So I'll break the wings,
I'll release it, and then I'll grab it. Okay, which would work
if you think that משלח meshaleach means to let it walk away,
not even to let it fly away.
But also wouldn't you do the שלוח? shiluach?
Yeah, but he did it here when he was supposed to.
But you couldn't use it though, you couldn't eat it? Why? Because
of broken wings?
Oh, I don't know, I mean, I mean—oh, right, because it would
make it a
טריפה?
treifa? It's a defect.
No, a מום mum I don't know, it would have to be
a טריפה. treifa. So I mean it's only if it—well
what if
he's missing a wing, that's a טריפה? treifa? It's not missing.
Yeah, now you're—ah, you see this is appropriate for doing a סיום
siyum on חולין, Chullin, you're trying to make me remember the טריפות
treifot of birds. So
I don't know, good question. Maybe he just—I don't know, maybe he
just tied its wings up to its body, but that's not what
it says. Somehow it's possible, I think, to do it without it
being a טריפה. treifa. Alright, so it's a good point though. Maybe
he was going to use it for dog food, I don't know.
Anyway, ואחר כך תפסה, ve-acharach kach tafsa, and then he grabbed it.
נגדיה רב יהודה. Nagdei Rav Yehuda. So Rav Yehuda lashed him. רב
יהודה, Rav Yehuda, who remember was the one that says that you
have to let it fly away, so he for him this certainly
would not have constituted sending away the bird, so he gave him
lashes, rabbinic lashes. It does not seem to be biblical. We'll talk
about that in a minute. אמר ליה זיל רביי ליה גדפיה, Amar
lei zil rabei lei gadfei, go take wait, don't eat it, wait
till its wings grow back. Okay, so there גזינהו gazinhu actually here,
here is the real answer to your Rivka is that I mistranslated.
גזינהו gazinhu is not grow, גזינהו gazinhu means to shear. Yes, he
sheared the wings, right. That's the real answer. That also of course
is clear, right,
it's dripping, clipped the wings, right. That's the real answer. That's clear
also from the continuation of the story, but that's like we just
read about גז ראשית הגז. gez reishis ha-gez. גזינהו gazinhu is to
shear. Okay, so he sheared the wings and then he said, "Go
wait till the wings grow back, ושלח ve-shalach and then you'll send
it off so you can do the מצווה mitzvah of שלוח." shiluach.
And according to him, the מצווה mitzvah of שלוח shiluach required it
flying. So the גמרא Gemara says, "כמאן, kiman, one minute, who are
you going like? אי כרבי יהודה, ei k'Rabbi Yehuda, if it's like
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda of the משנה Mishna that says that even
sending it afterwards, I've got to turn this up, okay anyway, so
we're sorry you'll get that. Okay fine. If it's like רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda of the משנה Mishna that says even after you've violated
you cannot fix the transgression by sending away the mother bird, then
לוקה ואינו משלח. loka ve'eino meshalleach. Then why are you telling him
to send the bird away? Give him the lashes because he violated
and you can't fix it once you've violated. אי רבנן, ei Rabbanan,
if it's the רבנן Rabbanan of the משנה, Mishna, so they say
the sending away fixes the transgression as it were, משלח ואינו לוקה,
meshalleach ve'eino loka, so far wait for the wings to grow back,
send it away, but why did you give him lashes? Since he
sent it away, that should exempt him from lashes. So the גמרא
Gemara says, "לעולם כרבנן, le'olam k'Rabbanan, really it is the רבנן Rabbanan
and really you're right, he's exempt from biblical lashes. But anyway, nobody's
administering biblical lashes nowadays anyway. So we're not talking about biblical lashes,
what are we talking about? ומכת מרדות מדרבנן. u'makkas mardus mi-derabbanan. It
is rabbinic lashes. Yes, that they were doing all the time in
the גמרא, Gemara, rabbinic lashes. Not anymore, but in the time of
the גמרא. Gemara. מרדות mardus is rebellious, meaning it's lashes that are
not the formal punishment in the תורה Torah for transgression but it
is the rabbinic administered lashes that don't have any of the specific
criteria, that is done because for people that are acting in a
rebellious manner. So it's done for various types of social control and
at the rabbis' discretion, although sometimes there were fixed rules when you
give it, but very often it was at their discretion. So basically
he's saying, you're right, biblically you're exempt from lashes because you eventually
you send away the mother bird, but this guy was acting in
a way which was obviously very subversive and therefore we wanted to
show control.
Sounds like what people hear and
what sounds like some people hear and some people don't hear. That's
a good question. There are different, yeah, why they choose one over
the other is I don't know, I mean it's a good question.
I don't know if anybody has sort of tried to systematically analyze
that. Okay, now I do want to make another point though about
this, a very important point, since we're in the context about the
rabbis saying that you send away the mother bird is how you
fix the transgression. And the rabbis say that שלח תשלח shalleach teshallach
is if you've transgressed. So the question that I ask myself is,
according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, if you don't transgress, you're going to
take the chicks and send away the mother bird, are you doing
a מצווה mitzvah by sending away the mother bird or is the
מצווה mitzvah only after you've transgressed? Right, they certainly say the מצווה
mitzvah is if you've transgressed you fix it by sending it away,
but do they also say you do a מצווה mitzvah by sending
it away from the outset? So interestingly, if you look at רש"י
Rashi when רש"י Rashi says earlier,
"עד כמה משלחה," ad kama meshallchah, it's like twelve lines down, it's
twelve lines down in the narrow lines, it's two lines under the
words י"ב yod beis in the margin between רש"י Rashi and the
גמרא. Gemara. רש"י Rashi says, "How do you send it away? Right,
remember that? אם נטלה, im netalah, if you took it." So it
seems that רש"י Rashi is trying to say if you've transgressed then
you have the מצווה mitzvah to send it away. That's what we've
been talking about according to the רבנן, Rabbanan, but it seems to
suggest that there's no מצווה mitzvah of sending it away at the
outset. The רמב"ם Rambam in when he talks about the מצווה mitzvah
of sending away the mother bird in the opening to הלכות שחיטה
Hilchos Shechita where he lists the מצוות mitzvos that he's going to
be discussing says, "לשלח את האם אם נטלה על הבנים," le'shalleach es
ha-em im netalah al ha-banim, something almost just like רש"י. Rashi. To
send away the mother bird if you've taken it. But then as
you continue to read the רמב"ם Rambam and in the ספר החינוך
Sefer HaChinuch and in others, they speak about the fact that it's
a מצווה mitzvah that applies even from the outset. So this is
very interesting. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda we know says it's only a
מצווה mitzvah from the outset. If you transgress, there's no point. The
רבנן Rabbanan who say if you transgress, then the תורה Torah is
telling you you can fix it by sending it away, would they
also agree that even if you haven't transgressed, the מצווה mitzvah of
sending it away begins at... Logically you would think so, you would
think that when I send away the mother bird, I'm not just
not doing the transgression, you'd think I'm doing the מצווה mitzvah of
שלח תשלח. shalleach teshallach. But it is interesting that there's a little
ambiguity about that according to the רבנן Rabbanan who emphasize that it's
coming to fix the transgression.
Very interesting, but what about if you actually want the mother bird?
What are you supposed to do?
You have no option. That's the משנה. Mishna. You can't take the
mother bird. You wait till the mother bird isn't hovering over the
chicks, but while she's hovering over the chicks, the only option you
have is to take the chicks. You cannot choose to take the
mother bird. And if you take...
so okay, so what are you supposed to do according to the
רבנן Rabbanan is in terms of שלוח הקן? shiluach ha-kan? It's only
if you took the mother bird...
well that's the question, obviously you have to send away... mother bird
not to transgress לא תקח האם על הבנים. lo tikach ha-em al
ha-banim.
But the question is, if I'm here's really the question. If you
say the מצוה Mitzvah שילוח Shiluach is only if I've transgressed, then
what I should do is I could go ahead and take the
chicks and ignore the mother bird, not do any act of sending
away, because then I haven't transgressed taking the mother with the chicks,
right? I've only taken the chicks, and the מצוה Mitzvah of sending
away is only if I've transgressed. So I'm just taking the chicks
and I'm ignoring the mother bird. So that's really the question I'm
asking. When you're taking the chicks, is there a מצוה Mitzvah then
to send away the mother bird, or is the מצוה Mitzvah to
send is only if obviously for us intuitively, you know, what are
you talking about? Of course the מצוה Mitzvah is that when you're
taking the chicks, you're sending away the mother bird. But I just
wanted to point out that there is some ambiguity in the ראשונים
Rishonim based on the fact that the גמרא Gemara emphasizes that according
to the רבנן Rabbanan this מצוה Mitzvah is coming to fix the
transgression
of taking
it, the mother and the chicks together, right?
So if you just take the chicks, yes,
and you don't send her away, that is
that's the question I'm asking. You haven't transgressed the negative prohibition because
you haven't taken them both, but I'm asking the question about whether
you have you also at that moment have a מצוה Mitzvah to
send away the mother or you're just prohibited from taking them both.
Obviously again for us intuitively obviously you have a מצוה Mitzvah to
send away the mother as well, but there is some ambiguity about
that. Okay, now let's get back to the גמרא. Gemara. ההוא דאתא
לקמיה דרבא, Hahu de-ata lekamei de-Rava, somebody came to רבא. Rava. אמר
ליה, Amar lei, תיימא מהו? Teima mahu?
What's the story with this תיימא Teima bird? Whatever that bird was,
it's some kosher bird, he wanted to know do I have to
send it away. אמר, Amar, so רבא Rava said, לא ידע האי
גברא דעוף טהור חייב לשלוחי? Lo yada hai gavra de-of tahor chayav
leshaluchi? What, this person doesn't know that kosher birds you have a
מצוה Mitzvah of sending away? What type of question is this? So
אמר ליה, Amar lei, he was trying to figure out what motivated
him to ask the question. So he said to him, דילמא חדא
ביעתא ההוא דרמי? Dilma chada beita hahu de-rami? Maybe it was just
one egg and what you want to know is whether you have
a מצוה Mitzvah to send it away if it's just one egg
or one chick, because the verse talks about multiple eggs, multiple chicks.
אמר ליה, Amar lei, הי! Hi! He said
yes, that is what my question was, that was the case. So
he says, ידיע לך, Yedia lach, so רבא Rava said to him
you should know, מתניתין היא, Matnitin hi, it's a משנה. Mishnah. אפילו
אין שם אלא אפרוח אחד או ביצה אחת, Afilu ein sham ela
efroach echad o beitza achat, even if there's only one egg or
one chick, חייב לשלח, chayav leshaleach, you have to send it away.
שדרה, Shadrah, so he sent it away.
והדר רמי ליה רבא פרשתיכא וצדה. Ve-hadar rami lei Rava parshatika ve-tzadah.
So רבא Rava laid a net for this bird. He knew this
guy was going to send it away. רבא Rava went out and
laid a net, so as soon as this guy sent away the
bird, it got caught in the net and רבא Rava was able
to then eat the bird. So the גמרא Gemara said an obvious
question, וליחוש לחשדא? Ve-lichosh le-chashada? Why not be concerned that that makes
רבא Rava suspicious, or not even suspicious, that it makes רבא Rava
look like maybe he פסק paskened this way in order that he
could benefit from it? You know, you don't want to have too
much of an obvious vested interest when you're פסק. paskening. It doesn't
make you look good. So
even if it's not influencing you, it doesn't look good. So the
גמרא Gemara says, כלאחר יד. Ke-le-achar yad. What does כלאחר יד ke-le-achar
yad mean? He did it with his left hand? So רש"י Rashi
says what it means is how's that going to help from suspicion?
So רש"י Rashi says it means that he wasn't personally involved. He
laid like he laid the net and then he left, and then
it got caught, you know, and he wasn't present when it got
caught, so it wasn't he wasn't obviously involved in capturing it. But
it is very interesting, you know, that in general there is a
question about פסק paskening on an issue that you yourself have do
have a vested interest. Not a בית דין Beit Din case, that
you're prohibited of course if it's a דיני ממונות dinei mamonot case,
but a פסק psak case that you have a vested interest. Technically
you're allowed to פסק pasken for that. What happens for me, I
usually, whether it's לחומרא le-chumra or לקולא, le-kula, you know, I don't
want to be too מחמיר machmir on myself but I don't want
to be too מקיל meikel on myself. So anyways, I usually I
know what I want to say but I usually anyway consult with
a colleague before it's anything that's נוגע nogea for me. But technically
you're allowed to פסק pasken for yourself. But here it's interesting that
the גמרא, Gemara, you know, at the same time that you might
be technically allowed, certainly you don't want things to be looking bad.
You don't want it to be looking like you are, you know,
like you're doing you're being motivated by that vested interest or you're
benefiting as a result from it. So so that's certainly what's being
addressed here, but the appearance is the issue, not the substance of
it. The גמרא Gemara is never is not actually concerned that רבא
Rava he gave him a straightforward פסק. psak. It wasn't a questionable
פסק. psak.
Okay, so question, can two people, the one person take the bird
and the other take the egg?
That
well,
the person taking the person one person takes the egg, well what's
the order? If one person starts by taking the bird, we saw
in the משנה Mishnah that you're over לא תקח האם על הבנים.
lo tikach ha-em al ha-banim. If you're taking the bird while it's
hovering, you're transgressing. So you can't take the bird first. So if
you took the eggs first, then even the same person after he
takes the eggs could then take the mother bird. The only point
is at that moment of taking the eggs, as we've been discussing,
it sounds like it's not just don't take the mother at the
same time, it sounds like then you do have a מצוה Mitzvah
to also send the mother bird away. Maybe it only has to
walk an inch, like it's ארבע אמות arba amot or it's דאתיא
תחת ידו, de-atya tachat yado, right? But then yes, even you can
do it. So I don't see how it would benefit by doing
it with two people. Even you can do it as soon as
you've done the מצוה Mitzvah of שילוח. Shiluach. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this, תנו רבנן. Tanu Rabbanan.
יוני שובך ויוני עליה, Yonei shovach ve-yonei aliyah, remember that we had
discussed before, the birds the the doves of the of the
dovecote and of the attic, so חייבת בשילוח, chayevet be-shiluach, those are
not considered under your control, so you're obligated to send
them
away, ואסורות משום גזל. ve-asurot mishum gezel. to be קונה *koneh* them?
What? That your חצר *chatzer*? But you can't קונה *koneh* something
that has no that isn't sort of settled in your yard. They
can fly away at a moment's notice. So that's not considered that
it's משתמר בתוך חצר *mishtamer betoch chatzer*. The only way that something
is קונה *koneh* in your yard is if it's protected and it's
sort of contained within your field. So you don't really own them.
So if they're now there in in Charlie's attic, these these pigeons,
and I walk into Charlie's house and I grab them for myself,
so so then it's not technical גזל gezel *gezel* because he technically
doesn't own it, but Charlie was planning on doing that and he
feels that he owns them, so it's דרכי שלום darchei shalom, *Darchei
Shalom*. Because of ways of peace, we treat it as if it
is stealing and I'm prohibited from doing it.
So those are only birds that are like really they're only birds
that are not under your control.
Right. Even those whatever those niches and the right. So the גמרא
gemara *Gemara* says ואי איתא *ve'i issa*, one minute, but if we
hold להא דאמר רב rav יוסי בר חנינא *leha de'amar Rav Yosei
bar Chanina*, here's exactly your question, Michael, the statement of רב יוסי
בר חנינא *Rav Yosei bar Chanina*, חצירו של אדם קונה לו chatzeiro
shel adam koneh lo, שלא מדעתו *chatzeiro shel adam koneh lo shelo
mida'ato*, a person's field and yard can acquire for them possessions that
fly that go in that are ownerless even without your intent. So
therefore you should not only be getting מפני דרכי שלום darchei shalom?
*mipnei Darchei Shalom*, Charlie should really own these pigeons. And if Charlie
really owns these pigeons, then there's also no מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to
send them away because there's no מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* to send away
if they're already owned. So then כי יקרא *ki yikarei*, only if
it chances, פרט למזומן *perat lemezuman*, to exclude a case when it
when they are already designated or under your control. So אמר Amar,
רב *amar Rav*, so now we're going to try to explain this
middle situation where where Charlie doesn't own them really and therefore I
have an he has an obligation to send them away. Why does
it not work because of his field acquiring for him? So we
are actually focusing here, it's interesting from the גמרא gemara *Gemara*, I
already jumped to the end, which is if you focus on the
birds, then it's obvious why the field doesn't acquire for him because
the birds never really full are never really contained by his yard.
But what is contained by his yard are the eggs. So the
גמרא gemara, *Gemara* is initially assuming that we're talking about the eggs.
So it's saying, look, why doesn't he own the eggs? And if
he owned the eggs, then why does he have a מצוה mitzvah
*mitzvah* to send away the mother bird? Once you own the eggs,
it's not כי יקרא *ki yikarei*, if it chances. So let's take
a look. So אמר amar, רב *amar Rav*, ביצה עם יציאת רובה
הוא דחייב בשילוח *beitzah im yetziat rubah hu dechayav beshiluach*. Once the
majority of the egg emerges from the mother, then automatically you would
be obligated to send it away. It's as if at that moment
you wanted the mother bird, even though it hasn't fully laid the
egg, it's only the majority has come out. If at that moment
you wanted it, you would have an obligation of sending away. מקנא
לא קני עד דתיפול לחצירו *mikna lo kani ad detippol lechatzeiro*. You
don't own the egg until it's fully dropped from the chicken or
whatever or the the not the chicken, the dove, and lands in
the act lands on the actual floor or in the nest itself.
So not when it's halfway out. So therefore what? דכי תני חייבת
בשילוח *dechi tani chayaves beshiluach*, when does it say that Charlie has
to send them away? מקמי דתיפול לחצירו *mikamei detippol lechatzeiro*. In the
scenario where what case where the egg is halfway out of the
dove, two-thirds out of the dove, at that moment Charlie chances upon
them, wants the eggs, and therefore he doesn't yet own the eggs,
they haven't landed. So in that case, he has to go away
and send away the mother bird. How he sends away the mother
bird and takes the eggs, it's not clear. Does he pluck the
egg out of the bird and then send it away? That's the
one scenario where there's not there's a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah*, the eggs
exist, but you don't yet own them. Okay, so גמרא gemara *Gemara*
says אי הכי i hachi *ei hachi*, if that's true, אמאי אסור
משום גזל *amai assur mishum gezel*?
Why assuming that that phrase about that I can't steal them because
of דרכי שלום darchei shalom *Darchei Shalom* is going on the eggs
again, not the mother, why is there a problem about even דרכי
שלום darchei shalom. *Darchei Shalom*, ways of peace, not taking it? If
the egg is not even really fully out, hasn't even landed in
his root, you know, in in his house,
in his roof, or wherever, in his attic, so there's not even
a דרכי שלום darchei shalom *Darchei Shalom* idea of גזל *gezel*. It
hasn't even fallen into his yard yet. So why is there a
דרכי שלום darchei shalom *Darchei Shalom* idea? אמר רב אשי באמו *amar
Rav Ashi be'imo*. You're right. The idea of that I shouldn't take
it because of גזל *gezel*, that's not on the eggs. The eggs
is totally ownerless, that's why there's also a מצוה mitzvah *mitzvah* of
שילוח *shiluach*. What does it mean I shouldn't take it? Because Charlie
feels that he owns it. That's going on the mother, not on
the egg, like we said it before. ואיבעית אימא *ve'iba'is eima*, if
you want, you can say לעולם אבביצה *le'olam abeitzah*. It actually does
go on the egg. So why is there a דרכי שלום darchei
shalom *Darchei Shalom* aspect on the egg? וביצה כיון דנפיק לה רובה
דעתיה עילויה *uveitzah keivan denafik lei rubah da'ateih ilaveih*. Even though technically
the egg hasn't even landed in Charlie's yard, but nevertheless, since the
majority is out of the is out of the dove already, and
we know that Charlie is so eager for it that he's already
grabbing the egg when it's half out and he's doing the מצוה
mitzvah *mitzvah* of שילוח *shiluach*, so once the majority is out, so
therefore it is like he feels that he owns it and therefore
there's a דרכי שלום darchei shalom *Darchei Shalom* aspect of גזל *gezel*
as well. Maybe that's true. But the point is that he's more
sort of can acknowledge his why he psychologically feels justified in owning
it once it's two-thirds out. Okay, and therefore there could be a
דרכי שלום darkei shalom. *Darchei Shalom*. So now we're in a very
highly limited and constructed case where you don't own the egg. Because
they're not they haven't yet really landed, but there's still a דרכי
שלום darkei shalom. aspect about them. Now the גמרא's gemara going to
go on. דהשתא דאמר רב יהודה אמר רב, dehashta d'amar rav yehuda
amar rav, אסור לזכות בביצים שהאם רובצת עליהן. assur l'zakos b'beitzim she'ha'em
rovetzes aleihen. But now we've got a better answer, because רב יהודה
rav yehuda said in the name of רב that I cannot, if
I've got, again, this case, doves in my attic that I don't
own that are laying eggs, I cannot take possession of those eggs
as אסור לזכות בביצים שהאם רובצת עליהן, assur l'zakos b'beitzim she'ha'em rovetzes
aleihen, that the mother is on them, שנאמר she'ne'emar for an obvious
reason, שלח תשלח את האם ואת הבנים תקח לך. shalach tishalach es
ha'em v'es habanim tikach lach. First send away the mother then take
the children. Now that seems to be obvious, like isn't that what
we've been saying, that you can't take the eggs? So we might
be saying one of two things. First of all, we might be
saying the issue I raised before, which is if there's only a
prohibition of לא תקח האם על הבנים, lo tikach ha'em al habanim,
right, don't take them together, and there's no מצוה mitzvah to send
it away until unless I transgress, so therefore there would be no
problem for me to take possession of the eggs under the mother,
right, because I haven't taken them with the mother? So maybe if
the whole מצוה's mitzvah, only afterwards there's no problem here? So he's
saying no, no, no, there's a מצוה mitzvah even if you haven't
transgressed to send away the mother. You can't take possession without sending
away the mother. Okay, and he might also be saying that maybe
it's not even about physically grabbing. Maybe if it's let's say in
my yard and I'm saying I want my yard to take possession,
to, you know, acquire for me those eggs, and I haven't physically
done anything, I'm still not allowed. My only right to take possession
of the eggs is only after I've sent away the mother.
But if קונה לו חצרו, koneh lo chatzero, it's already your possession.
That's what we're about to say. So hold on. Since I'm not
entitled to, let's say it's not in my yard, it's in the
forest, I'm not entitled to take possession. Now the other חידוש chiddush
might also be even if I'm planning on sending away the mother.
You have to do it in this order, that really puts the
מצוה mitzvah שלח תשלח shalach tishalach before, right, and not only after.
So first send away, even if you're planning on sending away the
mother, no, first you send away the mother, then you take possession
of the eggs. So you can't take possession first. So once that's
true, אפילו תימא אף על גב דנפל לחצרו, afilu teima af al
gav d'naful lachatzero, even if the eggs have been laid and they're
in my attic. Now your question is why don't I own them
already, but there's a logic. כל היכא דאיהו מצי זכי חצרו נמי
זכיא וכל היכא דאיהו לא מצי זכי חצרו נמי לא זכיא ליה.
kol heicha d'ihu matzi zachah chatzero nami zachyah v'chol heicha d'ihu lo
matzi zachah chatzero nami lo zachyah leh. If I can myself take
possession, then my field can take possession for me. If I'm not
entitled to take possession on my own, if I was in the
forest and I wouldn't be allowed to possess the eggs before sending
away the mother bird, then my field can also not be considered
to have acquired them for my behalf. Okay, so now we understand
why I don't own them. I don't own the mother because it's
never fully been, never really contained in my field. I don't own
the eggs because I'm prohibited from owning the eggs. But therefore, since
they are, the eggs have been laid and they're sitting entirely in
their attic or whatever, he feels he owns them, so there's גזל
מפני
דרכי שלום.
gezel mi'pnei darchei
shalom. Okay, so that is exactly, so that's exactly it. Okay, so
so but what we have actually decided here is not only how
to construct the case that there's גזל because of דרכי שלום, darkei
shalom but you know, that I don't own the eggs. But I
think it is very important from the point I'm saying about what
that the מצוה mitzvah. of שלח תשלח shalach tishalach for the רבנן
rabbanan is not only after you've transgressed but even before. And presumably
if we're reading this correctly, even if you're intending to send away
the mother bird, you're not allowed to, the order first had to
be first send away, then take possession. And because of that, right,
exactly. And because of that you can't take possession beforehand and even
your yard cannot take possession beforehand. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says,
one minute, now finally ask the question Michael's been asking. אי הכי
says the גמרא, Gemara אמאי אסור מפני דרכי שלום? amai asur mipnei
darchei shalom? So why is it דרכי שלום? Right, if Charlie's not
allowed to take possession of the eggs, why is there a דרכי
שלום aspect? אי דשלח, i d'shalach, if Charlie is going to, is
sending away the mother bird, then גזל מעליא, gezel me'alya, then he
really does own the eggs, then his field takes possession for him.
אי דלא שלח, i d'lo shalach, if he didn't send away the
mother bird, שילוח בעי. shiluach ba'ei. So then he's obligated to send
away the mother bird, and presumably he's not entitled to feel that
he has a right to the eggs, yet, what Michael's asking. So
the גמרא Gemara says בקטן. b'katan. So the question is okay, we're
not dealing with Charlie, we're dealing with Charlie's minor son, who actually
happened to be, owned this attic, okay? So for this קטן katan
he doesn't have a מצוה mitzvah of sending away the mother bird.
So because he doesn't have a מצוה mitzvah sending away the mother
bird, there's an aspect of דרכי שלום. Now why doesn't he really
own it then? Because a קטן katan can't really take possession of
things. So somehow we've got that all worked out that now it's
only a דרכי שלום because it's a very special case of a
קטן. katan. So the גמרא Gemara says קטן בר דרכי שלום הוא?
katan bar darchei shalom hu? One minute, there wouldn't even be a
דרכי שלום vis-a-vis a קטן. katan. He's not entitled to think that
he's taken possession of it. So therefore there wouldn't even be that
element. הכי קאמר, hachi kama, this is how to read it. אביו
של קטן חייב להחזיר לו מפני דרכי שלום. aviv she'lo katan chayav
lehachzir lo mipnei darchei shalom. So Charlie goes ahead and he takes
the eggs away from his son, okay,
and therefore he says no, no, no, so although I, if I
took the eggs from Charlie's son I wouldn't have to return it
because there's no דרכי שלום vis-a-vis the קטן, katan, there is a
דרכי שלום between father and child. So Charlie would have to return
it to his child although the child doesn't technically own it because
as a minor he's not entitled to own
it
in situ. convoluted case to explain this one. The simpler explanation would
have been to say that even though Charlie is prevented from taking
possession of it because of the מצוה, mitzvah? still the fact that
it's in his yard gives him enough of a feeling of ownership
that there's a דרכי שלום. But the גמרא Gemara doesn't want to
do that. He should sort of acknowledge that the מצוה's mitzvah, preventing
him and not entitled to his feeling of ownership and the דרכי
שלום. So that's why the גמרא Gemara completely shifts this to a
much stranger case of the קטן. katan. Okay? Yes.
You're asking that the מצוה Mitzvah. is preventing him to take ownership,
wouldn't the mother fly off for a minute?
Yes, and we're absolutely about to see that. Okay, another way of
getting around the מצוה. Mitzvah So let's take a look. Okay, so
גמרא Gemara. says,
where were we? Okay, so
לוי בר סימון, Levi bar Shimon, this person לוי בר סימון, Levi
bar Shimon, אחתי פירא דשובכא לרבי יהודה. achti peira d'shovcha l'Rabbi Yehuda.
He transferred
the fruit of the dove-cote
to רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, which means that the eggs and the
chicks, he transferred ownership of them to רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So
now רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda owns the chicks.
אתא לקמיה דשמואל. ata l'kamei d'Shmuel. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda came
to שמואל Shmuel to ask how to do this without having to
deal with the מצוה Mitzvah of שילוח הקן. shiluach haken. Okay? So
אמר ליה, amar lei, he said to him, זיל טרוף אקן, zil
trof akan, bang on the
dove-cote, דליגבהו, d'ligvahu, that they'll be lifted up, they'll sort of fly
up, הגבהה, hagbahah,
the chicks, וקנינהו, v'kaninu, and you'll take possession of them. Okay, so
meaning how do you take possession of a thousand little chicks? What,
I have to go and I have to take hold of each
one? He says, no, I got a trick for you that it's
like הגבהה hagbahah is a way of taking possession, you lift the
thing up. But you don't have to physically lift it up. You
can make it move, you know, go up off the ground. So
he says, bang on the cote, all the chicks will fly up
for an inch or two, and that's like you did a הגבהה
hagbahah on all of the chicks. And that's how you do it.
So now we think... No, the chicks. Now at least now we
think we're not talking about the מצוה שילוח הקן, mitzvah shiluach haken.
we're talking about how do you do a קנין kinyan on a
thousand little doves. Okay, so they fly up three טפחים. tefachim. It's
a debate, one טפח tefach or three טפחים. tefachim. But whatever, you
bang on the cote, they all fly up, you did a הגבהה.
hagbahah. So גמרא Gemara says, למאי, l'mai, what was the point of
that advice? אילימא למקני, ilei l'mikna, if it's in order to take
possession of it, ליקני ליה בסודרא. lishnu lei b'sudara. Okay, you don't
want to do הגבהה hagbahah on a thousand chicks, but do a
קנין סודר kinyan sudar with a handkerchief. Right? You just do a
handkerchief, that's symbolic, and that allows you to take possession of everything.
So גמרא Gemara says, אי ביום טוב, ee b'Yom Tov, let's say
it was ערב יום טוב erev Yom Tov and somehow, I don't
know, you didn't have a chance to, you wanted to eat the
chicks on יום טוב, Yom Tov, and therefore it's not so much
about a קנין, kinyan, but it's about designating. You wanted it to
be not מוקצה. muktzah. So therefore, you have your livestock and you
wanted to... what do you have to do ערב יום טוב erev
Yom Tov if you're planning on שחט shechting it on יום טוב?
Yom Tov? You're allowed to שחט shecht on יום טוב, Yom Tov,
but it's not מוקצה muktzah because your normal livestock you wouldn't be
planning on eating. So maybe you wanted to designate it. ואומר ואומר,
v'omeir v'omeir, זה וזה אני נוטל למחר. zeh v'zeh ani notel l'machar.
You don't have to do any physical act, you can just say,
I'm going to have this one and that one, and you can
just verbally designate. So that can't be what it was needed for.
So the גמרא Gemara says, no, here's the story.
הנו פירי חדתא הוו, hanu peiri chadatei hava, דלוי בר סימון גופיה
לא הוי קני להו. d'Levi bar Shimon gufei lo hava kani lehu.
These were new chicks that לוי בר סימון Levi bar Shimon himself
had not yet taken possession of, presumably it means that they hadn't
even... so again, I'm not exactly getting that because, you know, we've
just said חצירו של אדם קונה לו, chatzeiro shel adam koneh lo
I'm sorry, I am getting it because, right, fitting into what we
just said before, חצירו של אדם קונה לו does not work when
the mother is still on top because since you're prevented because of
the מצוה שילוח הקן. mitzvah shiluach haken? Now the question is, why
is there a מצוה שילוח הקן? mitzvah shiluach haken. Doesn't he own
the doves? And the answer again is no. Remember that even though
the doves have taken sort of, you know, residency within his dove-cote,
but because they can technically fly off, he doesn't possess them and
there still could be a מצוה Mitzvah שילוח הקן. shiluach haken, That's
why it's only דרכי שלום vis-à-vis the doves because you don't really
own them. So he doesn't own the doves, he doesn't yet own
the very chicks that they've laid, because even though they're in his
field, but you can't take
possession... wait a minute, you can't take possession of them until the
mother has flown away. Okay, so therefore he himself doesn't own
it. והכי קאמר ליה. v'hachi ka'amar lei. So he said to him,
זיל טריף אקן, zil t'rif akan, bang on the cote, what will
happen? דליגבהו, d'lis gavhu, the mothers will fly off a few inches,
and then וניקנינהו ללוי בר סימון, v'nikninu l'Levi bar Shimon, as soon
as the mothers are no longer hovering over the chicks, he's allowed
to take possession of the chicks, לוי בר סימון Levi bar Shimon
is allowed to take possession of the chicks, so his field automatically
takes possession for him, והדר ליקנינהו לך בסודרא, v'hadar l'nikninu lach b'sudara,
and then he'll be in a
position to transfer it to you even with this קנין סודר kinyan
sudar with this handkerchief. So now we have found out exactly this:
how do you get around this מצוה? Mitzvah. You make the mother
bird... you wait either till the mother bird has flown an inch
or two away, or you actually make it fly an inch or
two away, you then there's no מצוה, Mitzvah then you can grab...
and then you can go ahead and grab the mother bird. So
here the only reason you couldn't take possession of the chicks was
because the mother bird was on top of them and therefore his
field was preserved or his yard was prevented from acquiring on his
behalf. As soon as the mother's lifted up a second, he automatically
owned it and then he could transfer ownership, now that he owned
it, he could transfer ownership to רב יהודה. Rav Yehuda. So it's
a little bit distressing, I would say, that the whole פרק Perek
ends with a lot of technical ways that this can be avoided.
Okay? So let's go try to end on an up note here
with the last משנה. Mishna.
Why couldn't he own the mothers? Why didn't they arrange...
Because since the mothers can fly away, even if they're in your
field and have taken up residency in your field, they're not considered
נשמר בתוך שדהו. Nishmaer betoch sadehu.
It could have,
right, but this was, but then it wouldn't have been, but then
it wouldn't have, it wouldn't have fit the story because then why
would he have had to do this whole trick? So the case
was that yes, the doves...
No, then there wouldn't be a מצוה. Mitzvah. If you own the
mothers, there's no מצוה Mitzvah שילוח הקן. Shiluach haken. The מצוה Mitzvah
is only if you don't own either the eggs or the mother.
Wild birds. Wild birds that have taken residence in his dovecote. Yes.
Get that practical application today. Ducks and geese will often just take
up residence somewhere.
There you go. And since they're still wild and they can fly
off if they want, if they want, you don't take, your field
cannot be considered, they can't be considered controlled and possessed by your
field. No, no. Okay, so let's end this. לא יטול אדם אם
על בנים אפילו לטהר את המצורע. Lo yitol adam ima al banim
afilu letaher et hametzora. We discussed that yesterday. You can't do it
even for the sake of purifying a מצורע. Metzora. That מצוה Mitzvah
does not override. Of course, now we found a million ways you
can technically avoid it. You wait till the mother bird is hovering,
anyway, but okay, exactly, anyway, but if somehow you can't get around
it, then you, it's not overridden for the sake of the מצוה.
Mitzvah? And now we end by the following. ומה מצוה קלה שהיא
כאיסר, Umah mitzvah kallah shehi ke'issar, a tiny מצוה Mitzvah, that all
it costs you is like a dollar. Right? If you have to
send away the mother bird, how much does that actually cost? So
I don't know how much it would cost us, but for them
it was a very small value. We're only asking you to sacrifice
like a dollar for this מצוה. Mitzvah. אמר תורה Amar Torah and
it ends by saying למען ייטב לך והארכת ימים, Lema'an yitav lach
veha'arachta yamim, it'll be good for you and you'll have long days.
So קל וחומר Kal vachomer על מצוות חמורות שבתורה. al mitzvot chamurot
shebaTorah. How much more so for the more weighty מצוות, Mitzvot, the
מצוות Mitzvot that demand more from you, how much more will your
reward be great? כיבוד אב ואם
Kibbud
av va'em is a lot harder. Same thing.
Okay, now we're going to talk about כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud av
va'em. תניא, Tanya, we find a ברייתא, Braisa, so we'll end with
a little aggadic statement. דברי רבי יעקב אומר אין לך כל מצוה
ומצוה שבתורה שמתן שכרה בצדה שאין תחיית המתים תלויה בה. Divrei Rabbi
Yaakov omer ein lecha kol mitzvah umitzvah shebaTorah shemattan secharah betzidah she'ein
techiyat hametim teluyah bah. There's no מצוה Mitzvah in the תורה Torah
that immediately, that right there tells you you'll be
rewarded, that it doesn't really refer to תחיית המתים. Techiyat hametim. Now
what does that mean? It means that in a way חז"ל Chazal
were really bothered because the תורה Torah is consistently promising rewards, this-worldly
rewards, ונתתי גשמיכם בעתם, Venatati gishmeichem be'itam, למען יאריכון ימיך, Lema'an ya'arichun
yamecha, this-worldly rewards for the מצוות. Mitzvot. And you look around and
it doesn't exactly work. And it certainly did not really work so
well in the time of חז"ל Chazal after having suffered all of
the Hadrianic persecutions and so on. And how do you reconcile that
with the rewards of the תורה? Torah? So obviously, it's a question
that is asked regularly in the גמרא. Gemara And the basic answer
is those will be rewards for עולם הבא. Olam haba. Those rewards
are ultimately intended for the future world, not for this world. So
now we're sort of twisting that as a problem with an answer
for actually, we're already coming sort of armed with the answer. We're
saying when the תורה Torah says long days, you should know that
it's really promising you עולם הבא. Olam haba. Okay, because it doesn't
always work in this world, so it's really promising you עולם הבא.
Olam haba. אין תחיית המתים, Ein techiyat hametim, it's really about
the תחיית המתים. Techiyat hametim. בכיבוד אב ואם כתיב, Bekibbud av va'em
ketiv, it says by honoring your parents, למען יאריכון ימיך ולמען ייטב
לך. Lema'an ya'arichun yamecha ulema'an yitav lach.
בשילוח הקן כתיב, Beshiluach haken ketiv, למען ייטב לך והארכת ימים. Lema'an
yitav lach veha'arachta yamim. So that's what it says, you're going to
get long days. But look, it doesn't work. הרי שאמר לו אביו,
Harei she'amar lo aviv, עלה לבירה, Aleh lebira, let's say your father
said to you, a father said to his son, go up to
that tower, והבא לי גוזלות, Vehavi li gozalot, and bring me the
little chicks. Okay, so you're doing, the kid is doing a מצוה
Mitzvah. of כיבוד אב ואם. Kibbud av va'em. ועלה, Ve'alah, and he
went up, ושלח את האם, Veshillach et ha'em, and he did another
מצוה Mitzvah of הארכת ימים. Ha'arachat yamim. He sent away the mother
bird, ולקח את הבנים, Velakach et habanim, and he took the chicks.
ובחזרתו, Ubahazarato, and as he's going down the tower, נפל ומת, Nafal
vamet, he fell and died. So how are you going to explain
that scenario? היכן אריכות ימיו של זה? Heichan arichut yamav shel zeh?
Where's his long days? היכן טובתו של זה? Heichan tovato shel zeh?
Where is it'll be good for him? אלא, Ella, so clearly the
פסוקים Pesukim cannot be referring to this-worldly reward because we know it
doesn't work. So למען יאריכון ימיך Lema'an ya'arichun yamecha בעולם שכולו ארוך.
ba'olam shekulo aroch. Long days in the day that's forever long, in
the world to come.
ולמען ייטב לך Ulema'an yitav lach בעולם שכולו טוב, ba'olam shekulo tov,
the period that is always good. You'll get עולם הבא. Olam haba.
That is the only thing what it must mean. And therefore the
reward is even greater than you might have expected because it's promising
you עולם הבא. Olam haba. So this obviously does two things: it
solves the question of theodicy, right? It's an answer to that problem
and to the contradiction of the verses. And it also promises you
an even greater reward than you would have expected. So now the
גמרא Gemara says... ודילמא לא הוה הכי? Vidilma lo hava hachi? Why,
how can you ask a question like that? Maybe such a case
never occurred. Maybe anybody who does כיבוד אב ואם Kibud Av Va'em
and anybody who does שילוח הקן, Shiluach Haken, maybe they actually do
live a long life. How do you know to ask that question?
So the גמרא Gemara, says רבי יעקב מעשה חזא. Rabbi Yaakov ma'aseh
chaza. רבי יעקב Rabbi Yaakov saw exactly that case. So therefore he
had to come up with this answer. So the גמרא Gemara says,
nevertheless, maybe there's other explanations. ודילמא מהרהר בעבירה הוה? Vidilma meharher ba'aveira
hava? Maybe the kid was thinking about planning to do a sin,
and that's why he was suffering, because that, I mean, you could
still say, how does that weigh against the promise of the good?
But maybe that somehow undercut it. So the גמרא Gemara says, no,
מחשבה רעה אין הקדוש ברוך הוא מצרפה למעשה. Machshava ra'ah ein Hakadosh
Baruch Hu mitzarfah lema'aseh. God does not count your bad thoughts as
if you did it. So therefore that would not have been a
reason to have suffered that punishment.
ודילמא מהרהר בעבודה זרה הוה? Vidilma meharher ba'avoda zara hava? Maybe the
kid was planning to worship עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, which God does
count to your discredit, sort of to your, you know, negative tabulation.
דכתיב, Dechtiv, as it says, למען תפוש את בית ישראל בלבם, Lema'an
tfos et beit Yisrael belibam, to grab the house of Israel, to
seize them in their thoughts, in their heart, and we say that
that means that thoughts of
עבודה זרה Avoda Zara you are held accountable for. ואמר רב אחא
בר יעקב זו מחשבת עבודה זרה. Ve'amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov zu
machshevet avoda zara. That's thoughts of עבודה זרה. Avoda Zara. גמרא Gemara
says, no, הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. This is what he means. אם
איתא דאיכא שכר מצוה בהאי עלמא. Im ita de'ika schar mitzvah behai
alma. If there really was, and now you see that we're abstracting
it to a very general statement, actually this is something, a way
it's phrased sometimes in this discussion in the גמרא, Gemara שכר מצוה
בהאי עלמא איכא או ליכא. Schar mitzvah behai alma ika o leka.
Do you really get שכר Schar for מצוות Mitzvot in this world
at all? Is there any this-world translation for מצוות? Mitzvot? My wife
was brought up with a very פרום Frum and guilt-ridden background, so
whenever something good happens, like we find a parking space in Manhattan
or whatever, she says that's it, we're using up all our עולם
הבא. Olam Haba. So
anyway, so that's like very, there could be שכר מצוה Schar mitzvah
in this world, it's always a trade-off. Anyway, he said like this,
if you really think there's שכר מצוה Schar mitzvah in this world,
then תהני ליה ותגני ליה. Tehanei lei vetagnei lei. Even if he
was thinking about עבודה זרה, Avoda Zara, if the פסוקים Psukim somehow
mean a this-worldly translation, then if you're doing these two מצוות Mitzvot
of כיבוד אב ואם Kibud Av Va'em and sending away the mother
bird, you shouldn't have died. Maybe you'll, something will happen because of
your sins, but you shouldn't have died. So obviously the פסוקים Psukim
do not mean anything this-worldly. Okay, דלא ליתי לידי הרהור. Delo leiti
lidei hirhur. And now I actually sort of explained it a little
different. The גמרא Gemara says how should it have protected you? Not
that it should have counterbalanced your punishment, but it even goes further,
דלא ליתי לידי הרהור ולחטי. Delo leiti lidei hirhur velichti. It should
have prevented him from having had those thoughts. That's actually a little
bit also raises other issues about בחירה חופשית Bechira chofshit and so
on. So it's interesting that it moves that way. But the point
still is that if we translated the
פסוקים Psukim this-worldly, it would not, it still would be no way
to justify how he suffered this type of a thing. So it
must mean that we translate the reward in these פסוקים Psukim in
an otherworldly type of
a reward. Right, right, right. Exactly. אלא שכר מצוה בהאי עלמא ליכא.
Ela schar mitzvah behai alma leka. We have to conclude that you
don't really get the benefit of your מצוות Mitzvot in this world
and the פסוקים Psukim are interpreted through the world to come. גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, I don't get it anyway. Even if you
don't get the benefit of מצוות, Mitzvot, והאמר רבי אלעזר שלוחי מצוה
אינן ניזוקין? Veha'amar Rabbi Elazar shluchei mitzvah einan nizokin? Aren't you protected
when you're on your way to do a מצוה? Mitzvah So not
as a reward for the מצוה, Mitzvah. but as a protection that
comes, that's afforded through the doing of the מצוה. Mitzvah? People that
are going to do a מצוה are not, do not suffer injury.
So גמרא Gemara says, בחזרתם שאני. Bechazaratam shani. No, on the way
back, you're no longer doing the מצוה. So therefore you're not protected.
והאמר רבי אלעזר שלוחי מצוה אינן ניזוקין לא בהליכתן ולא בחזרתן, Veha'amar
Rabbi Elazar shluchei mitzvah einan nizokin lo behalichatan velo bechazaratam, that they're
not,
that they're not
damaged on their way and on when they return. So why then
that protection? Exactly.
So the גמרא Gemara says, סולם רעוע הוה. Sulam ra'ua hava. It
was a shaky ladder, ומקום דקביע היזיקא שאני. Umakom dekavia heizika shani.
And if there is established danger, meaning serious, you know, if it's
a very dangerous place, it protects you from unlikely types of events.
If there's, if you're really
exposing yourself to serious danger, the fact that you're doing a מצוה
won't protect you. It's interesting the גמרא Gemara didn't say that that's
maybe also why he didn't merit the reward. Maybe the reward also
does not counteract very great and present danger, doesn't protect you from,
you know, from obvious things in the physical world. But the גמרא
Gemara doesn't say that. It believes that if he would have, that
if the פסוקים Psukim were to be interpreted this-worldly, it would have
protected him even from a shaky ladder. דכתיב, Dechtiv, I don't,
meaning what? Well, let's just finish. דכתיב ויאמר שמואל איך אלך ושמע
שאול והרגני. Dechtiv vayomer Shmuel eich elech veshama Shaul veharagani. שמואל Shmuel
said, how will I go to anoint דוד, David, שאול Shaul will
hear, he'll kill me. So therefore we see that even though, what,
why was he bothered? He was a שליח מצוה. Shliach mitzvah. So
we see, no, when there's שכיח היזיקא, Shchiach heizika, that's usually the
phrase, not קביע היזיקא, Kavia heizika, שכיח Shchiach is a little bit
clearer, when damage is prevalent, is very likely, going to do a
מצוה won't protect you. So the גמרא Gemara says, why wasn't he
protected? Forget reward for the מצוה. Why wasn't he protected because he
was doing, going to do a מצוה? And the answer is because
the danger was great. But it's interesting the גמרא Gemara could have
used that to explain also why he didn't receive his reward, because
the reward doesn't override very great and
present danger. pushes the גמרא Gemara to say what anyway the גמרא
wants to say for, you know, because obviously this is not just
a question of this פסוק. pasuk. It's a much larger question about
why did you suffer if the תורה Torah is always promising us
all of these rewards and the major answer to that question is
עולם הבא. Olam Ha-Ba.
So what do you do with פסוקים pesukim like והשקימכם בעתו? ve-hashkimchem
be-ito? I mean that you can't say בעולם שכולו טוב. be-olam she-kulo
tov.
All right, so whatever, look at the רמב"ן Ramban there, he says
when כלל ישראל Klal Yisrael is keeping the מצוות. mitzvot. Anyway, let's
go on. So אמר אביי, Amar Abaye, no wait, אמר רב יוסף,
Amar Rav Yosef, אלמלא דרשה אחר להאי קרא כרבי יעקב בר ברתי
Ilmale darsha Acher le-hai kra ke-Rabbi Yaakov bar Bartei had אחר, Acher,
right, אלישע בן אבויה Elisha ben Avuyah known to interpret the verse
like we have just interpreted it, that it's talking about other-worldly reward
and not this-worldly reward, so then לא חטא, lo chata, he would
not have sinned, he wouldn't have gone off the דרך derech and
become an אפיקורוס. epikoros. So מאי חזא, mai chaza, so what did
he see that led him to lose his faith? איכא דאמרי כי
האי מעשה חזא. ika de-amri ki hai maaseh chaza. Just this story.
A kid going up to do שילוח הקן, shiluach ha-ken, doing two
מצוות mitzvot promised long life, and he died. And therefore he lost
faith. ואיכא דאמרי, Ve-ika de-amri, others say, לישנא דרבי חוצפית המתורגמן lishna
de-Rabbi Chutzpit Ha-Meturgeman and this is very powerful because it pulls together
what's really, you know, the urgency of the גמרא to develop a
different type of a theology, or this type of a theology, is
because he saw the tongue of רבי חוצפית המתורגמן, Rabbi Chutzpit Ha-Meturgeman,
רבי חוצפית Rabbi Chutzpit was one of the עשרה הרוגי מלכות, Asarah
Harugei Malchut, דהוה מוטלת באשפה, da-havah mutlet be-ashpah, it was cast in
the dunghill. אמר, right, because he was one of the people that
was persecuted in the Hadrianic persecution. So אמר, he said, פה שהפיק
מרגליות ילחך עפר? peh she-hepik margaliyot yilachech afar? This mouth that like
literally that, you know, out of this mouth came pearls, it now
shall be licking the dust? So how could it be that where's
the reward of the תורה? Torah? It must be the תורה Torah
is false, he said, and he left and he abandoned תורה. Torah.
והוא לא ידע, Ve-hu lo yada, he didn't know to interpret למען
ייטב לך, בעולם שכולו טוב, ולמען יאריכון ימיך, בעולם שכולו ארוך. lemaan
yitav lach be-olam she-kulo tov u-lemaan yaarichun yamecha be-olam she-kulo aroch. He
did not know that you could have said that that, now does
it mean he didn't know that that was a possibility or he
didn't believe that that was a possibility? Like in, particularly also, you
know, because, you know, sort of the whole Greek culture was obviously
very this-worldly. So you know, maybe he said he refused to think
that. He thinks the תורה Torah is really promising this-worldly reward. You
know, again, another way to step it back is it's not just
a problem about how do you make sense out of a פסוק.
pasuk. You know, you take it step back and here you see
the Jews are persecuted and are suffering, you know, the Hadrianic persecutions
and all of the great rabbis are being persecuted. How, where is
God's promise? How can we really believe in the תורה? Torah? And
that leads him to abandon the faith as and the גמרא saying
is, no, what we have to do is we have to have
faith that this ultimately there will be an ultimate reward even if
we can't see it. It is quite fascinating, and I'll just end
with this, you know, that the גמרא sort of frames his his
sort of loss of faith in these terms, in terms of sort
of like, you know, giving up hope and not seeing God's promise
and the suffering and so on, you know, as opposed to other
types of, you know, sort of more sort of philosophical issues, which
you know, which I don't know if anybody who read As a
Driven Leaf,
you know, it's sort of framed it there as much more about
sort of being influenced by Greek philosophy and ארבעה נכנסו לפרדס, arbaah
nichnesu le-pardes, right, which has much more to do with sort of
which more like, you know, philosophical issues rather than, you could say
this is philosophical-theological, but it seems much more personal here, that sense.
And anyway, at least the פרק perek does end with all of
the challenges that we had about technical issues and the values of
שילוח הקן shiluach ha-ken and ways to get out of it. At
least we do end with למען ייטב לך lemaan yitav lach, בעולם
שכולו טוב be-olam she-kulo tov, ולמען יאריכון ימיך u-lemaan yaarichun yamecha, בעולם
שכולו ארוך. be-olam she-kulo aroch. So we should all be זוכה zocheh
to that not only in the next world but in this world
and be able to live a long life and to be many
many סיומים siyumim on מסכתות masechtos and on ש"ס Shas multiple times.
אמן. Amen. הדרן עלך שילוח הקן וסליקא לך מסכת חולין. Hadran alach
shiluach ha-ken u-selika lach Masechet Chullin. Okay, so we have just enough
time to read the end and to eat. I'm sorry that took
so long there, but I don't know what people's schedule is. Yeah.
No. No, we'll eat. Okay.
So
alright, I guess I'll read this. We might, we might be joined
by some of the guys from the...